Peter Marshall and Catherine Marshall Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Peter Marshall and Catherine Marshall Papers 1927-1964 1933-1956
MSS31468
Marshall, Peter, 1902-1949
Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983
10,000 items
31 containers plus 5 oversize
14.4 linear feet
6 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Presbyterian clergyman and chaplain of the United States Senate (Peter Marshall). Author (Catherine Marshall). Correspondence, notes, and sermons of Peter Marshall, and drafts, galleys, scrapbooks, movie scripts, and other papers about Marshall collected by his wife, Catherine Marshall.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Engel, Samuel G., 1904-1984--Correspondence.; Griffin, Eleanore--Correspondence.; Marshall family.; Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983. Beyond our selves. 1961.; Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983. Friends with God; stories and prayers of the Marshall family. 1956.; Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983. God loves you; our family's favorite stories and prayers. 1953.; Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983. Man called Peter; the story of Peter Marshall. 1951.; Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983. Peter Marshall and Catherine Marshall papers. 1927-1964.; Marshall, Catherine, 1914-1983. To live again. 1957.; Marshall, Peter, 1902-1949.; Marshall, Peter, 1902-1949.; Marshall, Peter, 1902-1949. God loves you; our family's favorite stories and prayers. 1953.; Marshall, Peter, 1902-1949. Mr. Jones; meet the Master, sermons and prayers. 1949.; Peters, Jean, 1926-2000--Correspondence.; Rambeau, Marjorie, 1889-1970--Correspondence.; Todd, Richard, 1919-2009--Correspondence.
Organizations
Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation.
Subjects
American literature.; Bereavement--Religious aspects--Christianity.; Children--Religious life.; Christian life.; Clergy--United States.; Faith.; Families--Religious life.; Motion pictures.; Presbyterian Church--Clergy.; Presbyterian Church--Sermons.; Religion.; Sermons, American--20th century.; Spouses of clergy--United States.
Titles
Man Called Peter (Motion picture)
Occupations
Chaplains, U.S. Senate.; Clergy.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Peter Marshall, Presbyterian clergyman and chaplain of the United States Senate, and his wife, Catherine Marshall, author, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Catherine Marshall LeSourd in 1964 and converted to a gift in 1970. Additional gifts were received, 1968-1969.
Transfers
Sound recordings and television tapes have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Peter Marshall and Catherine Marshall are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on six reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Peter Marshall
Date Event
1902, Mar. 27 Born, Coatbridge, Scotland
1927 Emigrated to United States
1931 Graduated from Columbia Theological Seminary, Decatur, Ga.
1931 Ordained a Presbyterian minister
1931 1933 Pastor of church in Covington, Ga.
1933 1937 Pastor, Westminster Presbyterian Church, Atlanta, Ga.
1936 Married Catherine Sarah Wood
1937 Named pastor of New York Avenue Presbyterian Church, Washington, D.C.
1947 Named chaplain of United States Senate
1949, Jan. 25 Died, Washington, D.C.
Catherine Marshall
Date Event
1914, Sept. 27 Born, Johnston City, Tenn.
1936 Graduated, Agnes Scott College, Decatur, Ga. Married Peter Marshall
1951 Published A Man Called Peter. New York: McGraw-Hill
1955 Film release of A Man Called Peter (motion picture)
1959 Married Leonard LeSourd
1967 Published Christy. New York: McGraw-Hill
1983, Mar. 18 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Peter Marshall (1902-1949) and Catherine Marshall (1914-1983), husband and wife, span the years 1927-1964, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1933-1956. Personal materials of Peter Marshall comprise about a fourth of the collection, including a small amount of correspondence and a large file of notes for his sermons. The sermons, about 850 in number, cover the period 1933 through January 1948 and include such well-known sermons as “Singing in the Rain,” “Go Down Death,” “Under Sealed Orders,” “The King is in the Audience,” and “Rendezvous in Samarra.” There are also synopses of many of the sermons and various indexes that list the sermons by title, date, location, subject matter, and quotations used. The collection is organized into seven series: Peter Marshall: Sermons, Peter Marshall: Correspondence, Catherine Marshall: Correspondence, Catherine Marshall: Book and Article File, Scrapbooks, Addition I, and Addition II.
Catherine Marshall's papers, in addition to treating her own career as an author and lecturer following the death of her husband, are mainly oriented to the life of Peter Marshall and to her biography of him, A Man Called Peter. Most of her correspondence consists of mail from persons who read her numerous books and saw the motion picture based on the biography.
A significant portion of the papers concerns the production by Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation of A Man Called Peter. There are verbatim records of the conferences attended by Catherine Marshall and representatives of Twentieth Century-Fox during planning of the film. In addition to many versions of the film script, these records present the metamorphosis of the work from printed page to celluloid. Important correspondents include screenwriter Eleanor Griffin, producer Samuel G. Engel, and the film's principal performers, Richard Todd, Jean Peters, and Marjorie Rambeau.
Also in the collection are other manuscripts of Catherine Marshall's published works, some of which include both original drafts and corrected copies of proofs.
The Scrapbooks series is composed mainly of printed material including some correspondence relating to Peter Marshall's election as chaplain of the United States Senate, his death, and Catherine Marshall's subsequent career as an author. Addition I and Addition II contain miscellaneous sermons and ideas for sermon, written prayers, seminary papers of Peter Marshall, and other material.
An appendix to this finding aid lists the names and dates of correspondents in the Peter Marshall: Correspondence series of the collection.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Peter Marshall: Sermons, 1933-1948
Peter Marshall: Correspondence, 1927-1956
Catherine Marshall: Correspondence, 1949-1961
Catherine Marshall: Book and Article File
Scrapbooks (Oversize), 1946-1960
Addition I, 1932-1946
Addition II, 1934-1964
Container List
- Peter Marshall: Sermons, 1933-1948 (Box 1-8, Reel 1-6)
  Texts of sermons by Peter Marshall and related material.
  Organized into two groups and arranged as filmed, with Group 2 preceding Group 1. Numbers to sermons were assigned by Marshall. Includes various indexes.
  Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 13,847
  - Indexes (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lists of sermons (incomplete) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Index to locations of sermons (incomplete) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Synopses of sermons (incomplete) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Quotations used in sermons (incomplete) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Subject index (incomplete) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Poems (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Lists of sermons, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Notebook, Christmas list (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Indexes to locations, (2 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Synopses of sermons (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Sermons (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
    - Group 2 (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
      - Numbered (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
        - Nos. 1-119, (12 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
        - Nos. 120-249, (14 folders) (Box 3, Reel 2-3)
        - Nos. 250-359, (11 folders) (Box 4, Reel 3)
        - Nos. 360-479, (13 folders) (Box 5, Reel 3-4)
        - Nos. 480-608, (14 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4-5)
        - Nos. 610-624, (2 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5)
      - Unnumbered (Box 7, Reel 5)
        - 1933-1948, (4 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5)
        - Undated, (9 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5)
      - Group 1 (Box 8, Reel 5-6)
        - Nos. 2-487 (some numbers absent), (10 folders) (Box 8, Reel 5-6)
- Peter Marshall: Correspondence, 1927-1956 (Box 8, Reel 8)
  Family letters and general correspondence of letters sent and received by Peter Marshall. Names and dates of correspondents are listed in an appendix.
  Arranged by type and therein chronologically.
  - General, 1937-1948, (3 folders) (Box 8, Reel 6)
  - Family, 1927-1956, undated (Box 8, Reel 6)
- Catherine Marshall: Correspondence, 1949-1961 (Box 9-13)
  Letters sent and received by Catherine Marshall.
  Arranged chronologically, with travel correspondence organized according to location and miscellany filed at the end of the series.
  - Chronological (Box 9)
    - Jan. 1949-1952, (16 folders) (Box 9)
    - Feb. 1952-Sept. 1953, (23 folders) (Box 10)
    - Oct. 1953-Feb. 1957, (23 folders) (Box 11)
    - Mar. 1957-July 1959, (20 folders) (Box 12)
    - Aug. 1959-Dec. 1961, (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Trips to Scotland (1951), Hollywood, Calif. (1957), Natchez, Miss., California, and Europe (1958), (8 folders) (Box 13)
  - Miscellany (Box 13)
- Catherine Marshall: Book and Article File (Box 14-26)
  Drafts and production material of Mrs. Marshall's published books and articles and an unpublished work. The manuscript of A Man Called Peter also contains papers concerning the movie version of the work.
  Arranged by title of work.
  - Beyond Our Selves, (11 folders); (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 14, Box 15, Box 16)
  - The First Easter (Box 16)
  - Friends with God, (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - God Loves You, (4 folders) (Box 16)
  - Let's Keep Christmas (Box 17)
  - A Man Called Peter, (17 folders); (15 folders); (11 folders); (4 folders) (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21)
    - Correspondence, Nov. 1952-Dec. 1955, (13 folders) (Box 22)
    - Option agreement, 19 Nov. 1952 (Box 22)
    - Movie conference (Box 22)
      - 4 Dec. 1953 (Box 22)
      - 29-30 Apr. 1954 (Box 23)
    - Background, (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - Movie outline (Box 23)
    - Step sheets, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Chapter breakdown (Box 23)
    - Working script (Box 23)
    - Working script, (3 folders) (Box 24)
    - First draft continuity (Box 24)
    - Temporary script (Box 24)
    - Revised final script (Box 24)
    - Shooting final script (Box 24)
    - Miscellany (Box 24)
    - Printed matter (Box 24)
  - Mr. Jones, Meet the Master (Box 25)
  - To Live Again, (14 folders); (2 folders) (Box 25, Box 26)
  - Requests to quote from Catherine Marshall's books, (6 folders) (Box 26)
  - “Journal of a Trip to Scotland,” unpublished (Box 26)
  - Articles, (3 folders) (Box 26)
- Scrapbooks (Oversize), 1946-1960 (Box 27-31)
  Mainly biographical material about Peter Marshall and publicity relating to the books and movie about him.
  Arranged in chronological sequence.
  - Peter Marshall's heart attack, 31 Mar. 1946 (Box OV 27)
  - Election as Chaplain of the United States Senate, 31 Dec. 1947 (Box OV 27)
  - Peter Marshall's preaching mission, Neosho, Mo. (Box OV 27)
  - Senate prayers clipped from the Congressional Record, 6 Jan. 1947-31 Dec. 1948 (Box OV 28)
  - Death of Peter Marshall (Box OV 28)
  - Publicity and reviews of Catherine Marshall's Mr. Jones, Meet the Master and A Man Called Peter (1951-1952) (Box OV 29)
  - Publicity relating to A Man Called Peter (1953-1954) and movie scrapbook concerning the film. (Box OV 30)
  - Catherine Marshall scrapbook (1955-1956) (Box OV 31)
  - Publicity concerning Prayers of Peter Marshall (1954-1955) (Box OV 31)
  - Publicity concerning To Live Again (1957-1960) (Box OV 31)
- Addition I, 1932-1946 (Box 32)
  Miscellaneous sermons, prayers, articles, and seminary papers of Peter Marshall.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Miscellaneous sermons, prayers, articles, and seminary papers, (2 folders) (Box 32)
- Addition II, 1934-1964 (Box 33-36)
  Material for sermon ideas, typescripts of sermons and prayers, and miscellany relating to Peter Marshall.
  - Senate prayers and other invocations (Box 33)
  - Prayer meeting talks, ideas, outlines, and drafts (Box 33)
  - Material for sermons (Box 33)
    - Alcohol (Box 33)
    - Biblical criticism (Box 33)
    - Books of the Bible, outline studies (Box 33)
    - Church and war (Box 33)
    - Doctrines (Box 33)
    - Education (Box 34)
    - Immigration (Box 34)
    - Marriage and divorce (Box 34)
    - Poems (Box 34)
    - Prayer (Box 34)
    - Predestination (Box 34)
    - Sacraments (Box 34)
    - Stewardship (Box 34)
    - Suicide (Box 34)
    - Worship (Box 34)
    - Notes, outlines and clippings, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 34, Box 35)
  - Sermons (Box 36)
  - Scottish Sermons and Addresses, galley proofs (Box 36)
  - Miscellany (Box 36)
    - Church records, weddings, baptisms, funerals (Box 36)
    - Doctor of divinity, degree, Presbyterian College, S.C., 1938 (Box 36)
    - Seminary class notes (Box 36)
    - General (Box 36)
Appendix: Index to Peter Marshall: Correspondence Series
General
Rustin, John W. to PM [Peter Marshall], Sept. 21, 1937
Harris, Frederick Brown to PM, Oct. 7, 1937
Stokes, Anson Phelps to PM, Oct. 7, 1937
Hughes, Edwin H. to PM, Oct. 25, 1937
Sprunt, Thomas P. to PM, June 14, 1938, with enclosure: reports of diagnoses study
McCartney, Albert Joseph to PM, Nov. 12, 1938
Peacock, Virginia to PM, Mar. 18, 1939
Marshall, Peter to Florence Lambert, May 4, 1945
Marshall, Peter to Mrs. Lionel Nutter, Oct. 3, 1945
Nutter, Mrs. Lionel to PM, Sept. 18, 1945
Hoover, J. Edgar to PM, Apr. 1, 1946
Hassett, William D. to PM, Apr. 3, 1946
Berghoefer, Bruce K. to PM, June 1, 1946
Hagedorn, Hermann to PM, Nov. 27, 1946
Sherier, James to PM, undated [telegram]
Loeffler, Carl A. to PM, Jan. 5, 1947 [telegram]
White House to Rev. & Mrs. Peter Marshall, Feb. 8-18, 1947
Truman, President and Mrs. Harry S. to Rev. & Mrs. Peter Marshall, Feb. 18, 1947
Hoover, J. Edgar to PM, Apr. 1, 1947
Wiatrak, Edward T. to PM, June 10, 1947
Marshall, Peter to unknown-Dear Betty, Aug. 13, 1947
Anderson, Howard Stone to New York Avenue Presbyterian Church, Washington, D.C., Oct. 13, 1947
Truman, Harry S. to Samuel Estill Whitaker, Apr. 1, 1948
Marshall, Peter to unknown-My Dear Miss Mary, May 28, 1948
Grapes, Maude to PM, Nov. 24, 1948
Haines, Dorothy L. to PM, undated
Family
Marshall, Peter to Barbara Marshall, June 20, 1927 [postcard]
Marshall, Sarah Catherine to Mother and Dad, undated [4 letters]
Marshall, Catherine to PM, Jr., Jan. 21, 1956
Marshall, Peter, Jr. to Catherine Marshall, July 7, 1947 [postcard]
Marshall, Peter [Sr.] to Catherine Marshall, undated